<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pronostycacyon practysed by master Mathias Brothyel of Rauensburgh. Anno. 1545</title>
            <author>[Brothyel, Mathias].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 420.15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110951</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17360)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 28:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pronostycacyon practysed by master Mathias Brothyel of Rauensburgh. Anno. 1545</title>
                  <author>[Brothyel, Mathias].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[28] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Richardus Grafionus [sic] clarissimi principis Edouardi tipographus,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excudebat Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1545]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C⁶ (C6 blank).</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 3842.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 3842 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative illustrated border enclosing title page</figDesc>
                  <p>A PRONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtycacyon practyſed by maſter Mathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Brothyel of Rauenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh.</p>
                  <p>Anno. 1545.</p>
                  <p>¶ <hi>EXCVDEBAT LONDINI Richardus Graftonus clariſſimi Principis Edouardi tipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:2"/>
            <head>The prologue.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The practyſe of maſter Mathias bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theyl of Rauenſburgh, vpon the yeare of the incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon of our Lorde Ieſu Chryſt. M. CCCCC. xlv. Wrytten for the pleaſure of the mooſt noble prynce and lorde, lorde Frederyke cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Palatine vpon Rhene, duke in Bauary. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doubte not moſt noble and benigne lorde, but that your highnes kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the texte of Moſes in hys fyrſt booke enty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled Geneſis, wherin he ſheweth and declareth that God almyghty created all thynges of nought, &amp; of none other thyng but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by hys deuyne worde &amp; breath of hys mouth, made all thys whole vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able worke of heauen, earth, the ſea and al that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is conteyned, aſwel viſyble as inuiſyble: &amp; that he doth yet ſtyl with out ceaſſing or intermiſſion worke what ſoeuer is done amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge al his cretures by the ſame his deuyne power. For in ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:11361:3"/> wyſe hath god (as ye wolde ſay) inward<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly powred him ſelf into al his creatures that al men (oneleſſe they be clene deſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of ſyght, or voyde of al reaſon) may ſe that God is contynually with vs, and that he gouerneth and ſuſteyneth all his creatures by certayne meanes, and ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth his diuine goodnes emonge al his creatures by the heauenly influences. And thys poincte alſo the mooſt wyttye and lerned men, I meane naturall Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, haue after a ſorte wel percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and through their awne reaſon and cleare wyt haue ſo ferre atteigned, that they haue agreed in thys, that there is one only God, &amp; that al creatures are by one certaine excellent diuine ſapience ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, vpholden and ſuſteyned. And theſe Phyloſophers alſo haue come ſo nyghe to the verite, &amp; to the knowledge of God in their hygh contemplacions, that they haue determyned and auouched al thys
<pb facs="tcp:11361:3"/> whole, wonderfull, fayre and ineffable workemanſhyp of God, as namely the heauens, the ſonne, the moone with all other ſterres and creatures, to haue ben created and made by the hygheſt artify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer &amp; chefe fourmer of al thynges. which God mooſt entyrely loueth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde &amp; fauoureth the ſame, becauſe he hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graued &amp; enpla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the hartes of men his diuine wyl &amp; pleaſure by the light of nature &amp; the enducyng of the lawe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, &amp; hath made mankynde an image like vnto him ſelf, &amp; his ſprite immortal incomprehenſyble, &amp; quycke or ſwyft of knowlege, much apt to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templacion, &amp; euermore hauing minde to his oryginal that is to God and to thynges ghoſtly, prone, diligent, fayne, &amp; much deſyrous. ¶ He hath furthermoe ſo ſenſybly &amp; vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſybly clothed &amp; couered the ſoule, with fleſhe, bloud &amp; other materiall ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce taken of the earth, and made it ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>le &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:11361:4"/> perceyuable to the ſence of touchynge, that it loueth earthly, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſytory, tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or mundayne thinges. Plato auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth man to be the ſoule onely, whiche ſoule hath the body but as a certayne ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bernacle and inſtrument. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is infuſed into the body, it is as ye woulde ſay obſcured or darkened &amp; (as it were) enbraked or enpriſoned in a derke dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ſo that it forgetteth all heauenly thynges, &amp; maketh ſearche to inquire of thinges vnneceſſarie, as what God doth in heauen, &amp; what thynges men dooe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them ſelues: &amp; not what thinges God worketh emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vs in the worlde by his creatures, as namely of the ſkye, the ſunne, the moone, &amp; the other planettes and of the whole fyrmament, where the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſelfes neuertheles ſhewe fourth hys ryghteouſnes, as wytneſſeth the Pſalmeſt, in ſuche wyſe that al thynges cha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces to come emonge vs in earth, do
<pb facs="tcp:11361:4"/> folowe &amp; enſue by the courſe &amp; influence of the ſky, &amp; by the reuolucion of planet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; of the ſtars fyxed. All which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges although thei be vnto your excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy manifeſt &amp; by your owne experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficiently knowen, yet ye may ſomewhat more clearely vnderſtande &amp; perceiue as wel by this pronoſticacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mine, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the practiſes of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this kind: that the Eclypſes of the two great lightes, &amp; of the other ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without doubte do induce &amp; ſygnifye great perels, of the worlde, &amp; diſſenſyons emonge thoſe perſons that haue the power of the world, &amp; be rulers &amp; gouerners in the ſame: which thing is of me in the chapters here enſuinge in this lytle worke of my practyſe in many places ſhewed &amp; declared. ¶ And foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much alſo as I know moſt noble prince your highnes by reſon of your noble ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues mete to be in a pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: &amp; furthermore
<pb facs="tcp:11361:5"/> by reaſon of a ſinguler prudence geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to you of God, that ye haue a ſpecyal incly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, &amp; a ſinguler affeccion towardes experyence, and towardes all artes. I haue thought it beſt in preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynge myne obeiſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; ſeruice, to dedicate thys my Pronoſticacion vnto your hyghnes, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſechyng that the ſame wyll accept and take in good part this my lytell la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. If at any time I can do pleſure vn to your hyghnes in greater thynges, I acknowledge my whole ſtudye, dylige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and trauayle bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de thervnto, yea and promiſe my ſelf alſo to be both prompt &amp; ready from tyme to tyme. In the meane whyle, beſechyng that God almyghtye wyll longe, kepe and gouerne your high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes proſperouſly in reaſt and peace, and lucky ſtate of al thynges.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>¶ Geuen at Monace <date>in the yeare. M. CCCCC. xliiiii. on the day of the Natiuite of ſaynt Iohn Baptyſt.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="astrological_almanac">
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:5"/>
            <head>A Pronoſticacion.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The fyrſt chapiter ſheweth of the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluence and effycacy of thoſe planettes which ſhal chefely beare rule this yeare.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T can not be denied but that the worde of God and the work created by his deuyne worde (that is to ſay, heauen, earth and al that is conteined in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) are ſo annexed &amp; vnited together, that it is impoſſyble to knowe the operacion of the one without the oth<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. For wylt thou knowe the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and ſtrengthe of the worde of God, then muſt thou ſearche in his workes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the which we naturally vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d what God worketh with hys creatures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and what he wil worke herafter. For here in earth n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt god almighty (as Ptholom<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in the fyrſt quadripartite techeth) al <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as wel of thinges to come as of thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that doth chaunce vnto vs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth through the heauenly, courſe &amp; influence
<pb facs="tcp:11361:6"/> of the planettes predominatinge or bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge chefe rule, who of al the mooſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert auctors in this arte of Aſtrology, is beſt alowed and folowed. Therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſawe wrothful and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencious Mars in the fygure of the reuolucion newly en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred into the houſe where Venus was, I may not geue the power of the hygher rule to the womannyſhe or femynyne planette Venꝰ, but ſhe agreeth with the angry Mars to be an aydour vnto her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherby Venus may gouerne this yeare after her wyl and dyſpoſycion. wherfore euery wyſe man wyll co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder the nature and propertye of theſe two planettes, &amp; ſo loke vnto theyr matters (through the deuyne helpe) that they fall not into the vngodly inclynacions of them. For it is wrytten, <hi>Vir ſapiens dominatur Astris,</hi> (that is) the wyſe man ſhall beare rule with the ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The ſeconde Chapiter is of the Eclypſes of the Sunne, and what tyme of the yeare it ſhal appeare, and of his operation i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> general.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:11361:6"/>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>literal depiction of the Gemini twins (Castor and Pollux) astride the dragon's tail (the descending node of the moon's orbit with the ecliptic) encompassed by the hollow circle of a moon</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſyxt day of Iuly, the moone ſhall take awaye from vs the light of the ſunne in thre poyntes .xliiii. ininutes in the .xxvii. degree of the ſygne Gemini, <hi>in Cauda draconis,</hi> or dragones tayle, and wyll make a ſhadow vnto vs, it ſhal begynne at .viii. of the clocke and one mynute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noone, the mydeſt ſhalbe .xlix. minu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes after .viii. and it ſhal ende .xxxix. mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes after .ix. of the clocke, and ſo it ſhal endure from the beginnynge to the ende one houre .xxxvii. minutes before noone And the operacion of it ſhal extende and teache one yeare .xxxi. weekes and thre dayes. Alſo in the yeare paſſed, on the .xxiii. day of Ianuary in the ſygne Aqua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius fel the Eclyps of the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, whoſe operacion laſteth two yeares .xxxvi. we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. And they that dwel in the Eaſt and
<pb facs="tcp:11361:7"/> towardes the South for the mooſt part ſhall feele the terrible operacion of thys Eclyps. And the operacion of it ſhalbe ſuche that ſcarſly I dare be ſo bolde to ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſe the terrible ſignificacion of it with wordes. For of truth mooſte myghtye prynce, euen thoſe vnto whom power to gouerne and rule perteyneth, are not fre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peryl &amp; operacion of this Eclips. For before that the terryble influence of the Eclyps paſſed, &amp; the Eclyps that ſhalbe in this yeare ſhal leaue their ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyons. Mars ſhall moue warre, and blowe his horne, chefely vnto the dyſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction and death of thoſe carnal or fleſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons that are fylled with vice and vncleanes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The thyrde chapiter treateth of diſcordes ſedicions and warres of this yeare.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lbehazen Haly the ſonne of A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>benragel wryteth in the eyght part of the .iiii. chapter, ſaiynge many perels ſhall chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vnto
<pb facs="tcp:11361:7"/> the warryers, that ſhalbe compelled to warre in the Southe: namely, when the reuolucyon of the yeare ſhal happen or fal in the day, and Mars beynge retro grade, or goinge backward in an earth ſygne. whiche thynge alſo Albumaſar in the .viii. difference of the .ii. tractes of the reuolucion of yeares, teſtifyeth: that when Mars ſhal occupy the .ii. houſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sunne in the ſygne Taurus, it ſygnifyeth much ſlaughter &amp; vniuſt ſhed dynge of bloude. Oh howe gredy, howe deſyrous, and thruſtynge for bloud that Mars is, whiche wyll ſpare no laboure nor payne to brynge hys vnnaturall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to effect. Oh howe louinge a maſter ſhal he be to diſcorde and enui, yea and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boue meaſure buſy and dylygent to ſeke occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſtryfe &amp; diſcorde. He ſhal ſtyre vp the courages or mindes of great me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; prynces to war &amp; battayle. For by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracion of theſe .ii. Eclypſes of the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and through theſe euyl and moſt vnfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate
<pb facs="tcp:11361:8"/> aſpectes of Mars and Saturne they ſhalbe wholy bent &amp; ſet vpon mooſt fyrſe and cruel battayle and warre. And as Ludouicus wryteth in the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his boke of Aphoriſmes or pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerbes of Aſtrologye: when Mars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge in the ſygne Cancer is burned with the heate of the ſunne, then ſhal his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, woodenes, and ferſenes be ſhewede more horryble in ſtyrynge vp of ſedycio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through al the whole worlde, &amp; to ſowe dyſcorde. And as then, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhalbe in the eaſt, there ſhalbe dyuerſe tumultes &amp; battels. All people ſhalbe at varyance &amp; warre at once together, which thynges almooſt ſhalbe lyke vnto theſe that are ſpoken by Aſtrage kyng of the Medes, that by the treaſon wrought by his nece or coſyn named Cyro, he had the victory of Harpurge. wherfore without ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, earneſtly and buſylye let vs offer ſacryfyce vnto the heauenly father, by Ieſus Chryſt oure Lorde, that he may
<pb facs="tcp:11361:8"/> wytte ſaue to haue compaſſyon on vs, &amp; to graunt hys holy ghoſt vnto our ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtrates, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the dyſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyons; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates, dyſcordes &amp; ſtryfes that nowe are ſpronge vp amonge vs, may beforgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And ſo together with God oure father without ende we may both reygne and lyue. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The fourth chapiter treateth of the frutes of this yere, and of the pryce of thoſe thynges that belonge vnto the vſe of man.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N diſcribyng, or ſetting foorth thys Chapiter, we muſte vſe a more exacte dilygence &amp; a more preciſe iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that we geue none occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to theſe engroſſers to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe &amp; occupy their engroſſynge, whyche do ſcrape vp and gather together out of all places &amp; coaſtes both wheate and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kyndes of graine, not only for their vſe &amp; profite, but alſo that thei may ther by get great gaynes &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore Albuma. wryteth in the boke entytled <hi>Floru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, de minus felici prouentu fructuum</hi> (that
<pb facs="tcp:11361:9"/> is) of the vnkyndly yelde of fruites: and ſayeth that when Venus is letted in the begynnynge of the yeare, and Mars is founde in the reuolucyon in Taurus, &amp; Iupiter in Caprycorne, that then there ſhalbe a great waſt of corne feldes, and a great dearth and ſcarcyte of all maner grayne and fruyte, aſwel of that which groweth on trees, as of wheat &amp; barly. And Ptholome alſo dothe wytneſſe the ſame in his boke entytled Centiloquium, in the .lxxxxvii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clucion where he ſayth when the fourth part of the yeare, &amp; the lordes of the corners of the preuencyon ſhalbe weake &amp; feable, that then al thing that do appertaine to the vſe &amp; profyte of men, to be both coſtly &amp; deare. But Haly Abe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ragel in the .xxxi. cha. of the fruteful &amp; vnfruitfull yeares ſheweth. when the lorde doth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fortunatly in the preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cional figure, &amp; doth turne him ſelf with a chereful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce to Iupiter, then
<pb facs="tcp:11361:9"/> the nature &amp; influe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the planettes are to geue vnto vs a very fruyteful &amp; ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful yeare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; a good &amp; proſperous yelde of al thinges, ſo that I dare boldly affyrme and truely ſay that the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de this yere ſhal yelde ſuffycyently al maner of fruy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; grayne to the vſe &amp; profyte of men. Furthermore, we reade in many places of ſcripture, as in the .xxi. of Geneſis. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the .ii. boke of Samuel the .ii. Cha. Amos in the .viii. cha. That there hath bene ofte tymes a great &amp; long penury of all thynges and intollerable famyn and dearth, namely we knowe this thyng to haue chaunced for the ſynful lyuynge of the people. So lykewyſe, euen nowe at this ſeaſon, except we amende &amp; correcte our lyfe, great and horryble plages ſhall enſue therof. For God is gretly offended with oure ſynnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The .v. chapiter is of the infyrmyties, diſeaſes &amp; plages, aſwel of men, as of beaſtes that ſhal reygne this yere.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:11361:10"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen in the ſcience of Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my I do conſyder &amp; ponder the cauſes of dyſeaſes &amp; infyrmites which chaunce yearely. I fynde that this yeare enſuinge ſhalbe peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and corrupt ayres, and there ſhal reygne a certayn general payne in mens heades of the whiche many ſhal dye, &amp; many by the reaſon of a whurlyng &amp; gydynes in the heade, &amp; of to muche melancoly ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be depryued of their wytte &amp; reaſon, &amp; fal mad, &amp; ſome other ſhal haue the fallyng euyl, &amp; many men ſhal dye ſodenly, and the peſtyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhal reygne in ſome places. ¶ Furthermore Mars &amp; Saturne do threaten verye whote &amp; burnynge diſeaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes: as feuers or agues, many aches in the head, necke, and in the eyes, and alſo impoſtu mes, pluryſes or ſtytches, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſondrye kyndes of dyſeaſes, with which God ſhal punyſhe the ſtyfnecked or inobedient perſons, for God doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes punyſhe the ſtubburne &amp; vnrulye people, as we rede in holy ſcrypture. As
<pb facs="tcp:11361:10"/> in Numeri .xvi. Deuteronomi .xi. Pſal. C. v. That the earth opened her mouth and dyd ſwalowe Dathan, &amp; ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of Abyrom, &amp; the flame of fyre burned many. Alſo ther is a nota<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble example wrytten in the Actes of the Apoſtles the .v. chap. of Ananyas &amp; his wyfe whych for lyenge &amp; dyſſemblynge with the holy ghoſt, fel downe ſodeinly. wherof the Pſalmody ſpeaketh. They ſodaynely went from God and peryſhed for theyr ſynnes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The .vi. Chapiter expreſſeth, in what dayes the newe moones, the quarters, and fulmoones ſhal appere vnder the fyrmament, with the chaunge of the wether for thre dayes before, or after, eyther of them.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ianuary.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He laſt quarter the .vi. daye at vij. of the clocke afore noone, colde &amp; drye with ſnowe, &amp; lyke wether ſhalbe on the .ix. day. The newe moone the .xii. daye at .xii. of the cloke .xxi. mi. at midnight folowyng, ſnowe, &amp; after with colde wyndes and tempeſt, myxed with ſnowe: The fyrſt
<pb facs="tcp:11361:11"/>
                  <choice>
                     <abbr>quart</abbr>
                     <expan>quarter</expan>
                  </choice> the .ix. day at .x. of the clocke afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cold &amp; dry with chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge of wether. The ful moone the .xxviii. day at one of the clocke xxxv. mi. before noone colde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">February</note>THe laſt quarter the .iiii. daye at eyght of the clocke after none, ſnowe. The newe moone the .xi. day at x. of the clock xxxv. mi. before noone, darke, cloudy and colde. The fyrſt quarter the .xviii. day at iii. of the clocke after noone, colde myxed with ſnow. The fulmoone the .xxvi. day at .vii. of the clocke after noone, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marche.</note>THe laſt quarter the .vi. day at .v of the clocke before noone, inconſtant, and after fayre. The newe moone, the .xii. day at .ix. of the clocke .x. mi. after noone, yet repayre not youre gardens, becauſe then ſhulde all the herbes peryſhe with ſnowe. The fyrſt quarter the .xx. day, at x of the clocke before noone. It maye be fayre vntyl the .xx. day. But March and Apryl wil ſhewe them ſelues angry and peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture they may let that. The ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moone, the .xxviii. day at .ix. of the clocke
<pb facs="tcp:11361:11"/> xxxviii. mi. after noone, Mars &amp; Venus wyll water the earth &amp; the feldes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let the huſbandemen prouyde to haue good ſeede of otes &amp; barly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apryl.</note>THe laſt quarter, the .iiii. daye at .xi. of the clocke afore noone, good &amp; tempe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate. The new moone, the .xi. day at .viii of the clocke xxviii. minu. before noone, moyſt, and after metely fayre. The fyrſt quarter, the .xix. day at .iiii. of the clocke in the mornynge, inconſtant, The ful moone, the xxvi. day at .ix. of the clocke .xix. mi. before noone, moyſt, &amp; varyable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">May.</note>THe laſt quarter, the .iii day at .iiii. of the clocke after noone, rayne. The newe moone, the .x. daye at .viii. of the clock xxiii. mi. after noone, moyſt &amp; cold, therfore be not to buſy to water the her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. The fyrſt quarter, the .xviii. day at x. of the clocke after noone, rayne &amp; wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, with thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; lyghtnynge. The ful moone, the .xxvi. day at vii. of the clocke xxviii. mi. aforenoon, fayre, but the .xxviii &amp; .xxix. day varyable with rayne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11361:12"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iune.</note>THe laſt quarter, the fyrſt day at .ix. of the clocke after noone, good wether to cary in hay, &amp; for reapers, but aboute the, v, day it chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth. The newe moone Eclypſal, the .ix. day at .ix. of the clock .xlii mi. aforenoone, rayne, thunder, &amp; lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge. The fyrſt quarter, the .xvi. day at noone, at which time I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel al huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d men to mowe their medowes of haye, &amp; to cary in a pace, yf they wyll not be let with raine. The fulmoone, the .xxiiii. day at ii. of the clocke, &amp; one mi. after noone with rayne aboute the .xxvi. day.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iuly.</note>THe laſt quarter, the fyrſt daye at, iiii. of the clocke before noone, fayre.</p>
               <p>The newe moone, the .ix. day at .xi. of the clocke .lv. mi. afore noone, rayne, thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, and lyghtnynge. The fyrſt quarter, the xvii. day at none, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate. The fulmone the .xxiii, day at viii. of the clocke .lix. mi. after noone, rayne and thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der. The laſt quarter, the .xxx. day at .ii. of the clocke af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter noone, fayre til the .iii. day of Auguſt, then rayne.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11361:12"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt.</note>THe new moone, the .vii. daye at .iii. of the clock .xx. mi. after noone, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perat and myxed with rayne. The fyrſt <choice>
                     <abbr>quart</abbr>
                     <expan>quarter</expan>
                  </choice>, the .xv. day at .ii. of the clocke after noone variable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ful moone, the .xxii. day at iiii. of the clock .xxxi. mi. after noon, moiſt not good to bathe, nor to let bloud. The laſt <choice>
                     <abbr>quart</abbr>
                     <expan>quarter</expan>
                  </choice>, the .xxix day at .ix. of the clocke afore noone, as afore.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre.</note>THe newe moone, the .vi. day at .vii. of the clocke .xxvii. mi. before noone, in ſome places much rayne. The fyrſt quar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, the xii. daye at .xi. of the clocke after noone, fayre &amp; conuenient to gather gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. The fulmoone, the .xx. day at .i. of the clock .xxxi. mi. after noone, a good harueſt ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient time to ſowe wheate &amp; Rye The laſt <choice>
                     <abbr>quart</abbr>
                     <expan>quarter</expan>
                  </choice>, the .xxvii. day at .x. of the clocke after noone, wyndy, &amp; rayne</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Octobre.</note>THe new moone, the .v. day at .xi. of the clocke .xxxi. mi. after noone, wyndye, yet fayre, about the .x. day colde, &amp; in hylly places ſnowe. The fyrſt quarter, the .xiii. day at .vi. of the clocke afore noone, ſnow
<pb facs="tcp:11361:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11361:13"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11361:14"/> The ful moone, the .xix. day at mydnight <choice>
                     <abbr>aft.</abbr>
                     <expan>after</expan>
                  </choice> xlvi. mi. fayre with drought. The laſt quarter, the .xxvii. day at fiue of the clock after noone, varyable.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre.</note>THe newmoone, the .iiii. day at .ii. of the clocke .xliiii. mi. after noone, cold and dry, &amp; a lytle after, wynde &amp; rayne. The .i. quarter, the .xi. day at one of the clocke af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter noone, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate. The ful moone, the viii. day at .ii. of the clock .xxxvii. mi. after noone, moyſt. The laſt quarter, the .xxvi. day at .ii. of the clocke after noone, cold &amp; moyſt, and in hylly places ſnowe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Decembre</note>THe newe moone, the .iiii. day at .iiii. of the clocke xxvi. mi. after noone, with colde &amp; varyablenes The fyrſt quarter, the .x. day at .ix. of the clocke after noone, te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perate, but about the .xiiii. daye moyſt with ſnow. The fulmoone, the .xviii. day at .vii. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clock ii. mi. afore noone, ſnowe. The laſt quarter, the .xxvi. day at .x. of the clocke afore noone, fayre, but aboute the .xxviii. day ſnowe.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11361:14"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
